A Guide to the Guide to the Virginia Department of Education Indian School records, 1936-1968
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Guide to the Virginia Department of Education Indian School records, 1936-1968
The Library of Virginia
29632
4 cu. ft. (5 boxes)
Virginia Department of Education
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The educational records of former students who are living are restricted until the student is deceased. If the former student cannot be traced, the records are closed for 75 years (2043). (20 U.S.C. 1232g; 34 CFR Part 99).
Acquisition Information
This collection was transferred by the Virginia Dept. of Education in 1976.
Biographical Information
After years of violent conquest at the hands of the English colonizers throughout the Anglo-Indian Wars, the Treaty of 1646 established Anglo designated reservation lands for the Pamunkey, Weyanock, and Chiskiack with additional provisions for the Mattaponi as well as at least nine other tribal groups. While the Treaty of 1677 at Middle Plantation reestablished these holding, subsequent colonial pressure and illegal seizures of land as well as Native population depletion from disease, violence, and forced resettlement saw that by the 19th century the only reservation lands, still diminished but enact, belonged to the Pamunkey and Mattaponi.
Prior to the Civil War, education was largely an individual endeavor reserved primarily for white elites who were able to afford the expense. This changed when the 1869 Virginia Constitution established the state's first public education system, and in less than a year an 1870 Act passed by the General Assembly dictated that the schools be racially segregated. As a result, localities prohibited Native children from attending white public schools and instead required them to attend schools established for Virginia's Black children. Instead of complying, many Virginian tribal groups created their own schools solely for Native children.
The Pamunkey and Mattaponi reservations worked together to establish, staff, and fund an educational network for their children through the 1870-1890s. While both operated schools on their respective reservations prior to the 1910s adequate resources and staff proved difficult to support. Then, as a result of the continual advocacy of Chief George F. Custalow of the Mattaponi and a 1916 ruling by the Assistant Attorney General of Virginia, Leslie C. Garnett, that as citizens of a reservation were "wards of the State" and not citizens of the locality (King William County, VA), the Department of Education agreed to allocate an annual sum for the education of Native children on the Pamunkey and Mattaponi reservations starting with the 1917-1918 school year for $1012.43.
In June 1950, the two tribes voted to consolidate into one school forming the Mattaponi-Pamunkey Reservation School in order to offer a broader and better program for grades 1 through 8. During the summer of 1950, the school building on the Mattaponi Reservation, which was to house the consolidated school, was completely renovated with many new facilities added since through additional State funds and donations from the Society of Friends and the Richmond Dietetics Association.
The majority of Virginian Indian children did not have access to high school courses locality (the Mattaponi-Pamunkey Reservation School only supporting a high school for a handful of years in the late 1950s-1960s). Beginning in 1946 in some areas by 1953, the State provided tuition and transportation funding for high school students to complete their courses at Bacone Junior College (Oklahoma), Cherokee Reservation School (North Carolina), Oak Hill Academy (Grayson County, Virginia), as well as various places in Michigan. This program, while marketed as an opportunity, acted as a continuation of the Indian Boarding School era by removing these children from their homes and communities to simply receive an education. After the fight for integration in Brown v. Board of Education and solidified in the Civil Rights Act, by 1965 Virginia provided integrated public education for grades one through twelve resulting in the closing of the Mattaponi-Pamunkey Reservation School at the completion of the 1966 school year.
In addition to the Mattaponi and the Pamunkey, the tribes most prominently represented in these records, other tribes of Virginia Indians and their schools also appear in the records including: the Rappahannock; the Chickahominy and Eastern Chickahominy of Samaria School, located in Charles City County (served Indian pupils from Charles City and New Kent Counties); the Upper Mattaponi of the Sharon Indian School located in King William County (served Indians residing in that county); the Sappony of the High Plain Indian School located in Person County, NC (served Indians residing in that county and Halifax County, VA.).
Scope and Content
This collection documents the educational activities of the Virginian Indian children and the administration of the Mattaponi-Pamunkey School by the Virginia Department of Education. It includes correspondence, memos, pamphlets, photographs, applications, architectural drawings, reports, grade books, transcripts, and other related documents.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into two (2) series:
Series I: Administrative Records, 1944-1968
Series II: Educational Records, 1936-1966
Contents List
- Series I: Administrative Records, 1944-1968., Extent: 3 boxes. (Boxes 1-2, 5)
  This series documents the administration of the school(s), their operations, and the boarding of students at schools out of state. Records include correspondence, annual administrative reports, meeting minutes, building agreements, commencement programs, equipment lists and orders, policies, contracts, newspaper articles, publications, photographs, menus, food items donated, requisition forms, and other records.
  Alphabetically
  - Subseries I: Administrative Files, 1944-1968., 28 folders, 1 oversized folder (Box 1)
    - Advisory Committee Meeting, 1965. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Annual Reports, 1955-1966. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Blank Forms and Diplomas. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Budget and Financial Reports, 1947-1968. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Building Agreements, 1958-1959. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Building Renovations, 1953, 1956, 1964. (Box 1, Folder 6, Box 5, Oversizedfolder 1)
    - Calendar, 1953-1966. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Crafts Programs, 1952-1956. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Commencement Programs, 1959-1966. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Dept. of Education Committee Meeting, 1953. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Dept. of Interior Correspondence, 1964. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Enrollment, 1964-1967. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Equipment and Supplies, 1952-1966. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Exhibit Day, 1954 May 21. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - General Correspondence, 1945-1964. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Historical Notes, 1955-1966. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Memos. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Newspaper Articles and Publications, 1951-1966. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Regulations, 1959-1966. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - School Census, 1950-1955. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - School Closing Procedures, 1960-1962. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - School Directory, 1964-1966. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Superintendent's Memos, 1960-1964. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Survey, 1955-1956, 1963. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Teaching Applications and Contracts, 1946-1966. (Box 1, Folder 25-26)
    - Teaching Permits, 1944-1956. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Transportation Records, 1960-1965. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Subseries II: Boarding School Records, 1944-1956. (Box 1, Folder 29-38)
    - Bacone College Correspondence, 1947-1955. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Bacone College Publications, 1944-1952. (Box 1, Folder 30-31)
    - "Bacone Indian" Articles, 1947-1950. (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Cherokee School Correspondence, 1952-1956. (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Chilocco Indian Agricultural School Handbook, 1948. (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Haskell Institute, 1953-1954. (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - High Plains School, 1951. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Oak Hill Academy, 1954-1956. (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Requests for High School State Aid, 1946-1955. (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Samaria School, 1949-1955. (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Subseries III: School Lunch Program, 1949-1966. (Box 2)
    - Program Agreements and Forms, 1956, 1962. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Program and Operation Documentation, 1962-1966. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Milk Program, 1954-1959. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Monthly Reports, 1949-1966. (Box 2, Folder 4-11)
- Series II: Educational Records, 1936-1966., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 3-4)
  This series documents the educational programming of the school(s), as well as the academic careers of the students. Included are attendance records and reports, grade books, reports on students at the boarding schools, curriculum files, book lists, high school transcripts, test books and answers, student registration, correspondence, and photographs.
  Alphabetical
  - Subseries I: Educational Files, 1948-1966., 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Curriculum Files, 1957-1966. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Educational Planning, 1948-1950. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Library Book Lists, 1960-1966. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Standardized Tests. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Textbook Lists, 1958-1966. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Subseries II: Reports and Registers, 1936-1966., 20 folders (Box 3)
    - Mattaponi-Pamunkey School(s), 1936-1966.
      - Daily Attendance and Grades (Mattaponi), 1936-1950. (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
      - Daily Attendance and Grades (Pamunkey), 1944-1950. (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Daily Attendance and Grades (Mattaponi-Pamunkey), 1940-1965. (Box 3, Folder 9-16)
      - Mattaponi-Pamunkey High School. (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - Monthly Teacher's Reports (Mattaponi), 1944-1950. (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - Monthly Teacher's Reports(Pamunkey), 1944-1949. (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - Monthly Teacher's Reports (Mattaponi-Pamunkey), 1950-1966. (Box 3, Folder 20-22)
      - Yearly Reports, 1944-1963. (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Boarding Schools, 1947-1956.
      - Bacone College Reports, 1947-1954. (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Cherokee High School Reports, 1951-1956. (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - Oak Hill Academy, 1955-1956. (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Subseries II: Student Records., 37 folders (Box 4)
    These student records begin partway through collection's timeframe, and do not list every student who attended the school(s). Students may also be listed in the daily, monthly, or yearly reports as well as reports from the boarding schools which may list name, age, and grades. The following lists only deceased students with individual transcripts in the collection.
    - Bradby, Joyce. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Custalow, Clayton. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Custalow, Curtis King. (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Custalow, Curtis Lee. (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Custalow, Delores. (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Custalow, Donald. (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Custalow, Joyce G. (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Custalow, Marie. (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Custalow, Marvin Ivy. (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Custalow, Philip. (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Custalow, Robert L. (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Custalow, Ryland. (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Custalow, Shirley. (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Custalow, Thomas. (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Goldstein, Joseph Ronald. (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Gundaker, Harrison Phillip. (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Gundaker, John "Jack". (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Gundaker, Mary Ruth. (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Langston, Ernest A. (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Pack, James Powhatan. (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Peterson, Chevis. (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Peterson, Geraldine. (Box 4, Folder 36)